Inventory of the Truman Smith papers, 1893-2002
Hoover Institution Archives
- 1980-1993 Increments, 1916-1992 (Boxes 4-16)
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, 1917-1992 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence and writings, 1965-1977 (Folder 14: 7)
      Includes typescript draft of "Polish Crisis--General Situation," transcript of conversation with Paul Thompson and Charles Willoughby, and correspondence with Frank Mason.
    - Accounts of events surrounding Austrian Anschluss, typed copies, 1938 (Folder 14: 8)
    - Clippings, 1917-1992 (Folder 14: 9-13)
  - Military personnel files of Truman Smith, 1919-1946 (Folder 14: 14-15)
  - Transparency of page from book on pilots during WWI, undated (Folder 14: 16)
  - Letters from Truman Smith to Katharine A. H. Smith during the Mexican Expedition, typescript copies, 1916 (Folder 15: 1)
  - Clippings and correspondence of Truman Smith and Katharine A. H. Smith, 1936-1985 (Folder 15: 2-4)
    Includes reviews of Berlin Alert.
  - Kniss, C., "Die deutsche Luftwaffenrüstung zwischen 1935 und 1939 im Spiegel der US-amerikanischen Attaché-berichte," master's thesis, undated (Folder 15: 5)
  - Published articles by Truman Smith, 1940s-1960s (Folder 15: 6)
  - Berlin guestbook, photocopy, 1935-1939 (Folder 15: 7)
  - Invitations and letters, photocopies, 1930s (Folder 15: 8)
    Originals in Box 22.
  - Photographs, negatives, and postcards, 1930s (Boxes 15-16)
    - Photographs (reproductions) used in "My Life, 1935-1939,", 1936 (Folder 15: 9)
    - Ambassador Hugh Wilson, circa 1938 (Folder 15: 10)
    - 8x10 negatives for "Facts of Life,", 1930s (Folder 15: 11)
    - Truman Smith and Charles Lindbergh, copy, 1936 (Folder 15: 12)
    - Photo album, 1935-1939 (Folder 16: 1)
      Contains mostly postcards from the 1936 Berlin Olympics, and some snapshots of friends, presumably compiled by Kätchen Smith in Berlin.
    - Transparency of identification document, undated (Folder 16: 2)
    - Postcards (copies) featuring Hitler and Göring, a zeppelin, and a rally, circa 1934 (Folder 16: 3)
  - "ETHE: A Tactical Study," typescript of lecture by Truman Smith and Major Richard G. Tindall, undated (Folder 16: 4)
  - Letters from Truman Smith to Katharine A. H. Smith, from France and Germany, photocopies of typed copies, 1918-1919 (Folder 16: 5)
    Originals in Boxes 18-19.
- 2010 Increment, 1893-2002 (Boxes 17-28)
  Contains correspondence, clippings, writings, diaries, ephemera, identification documents, printed matter, photographs, and microfilm reels.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged as they were originally received.
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, 1917-1924 (Boxes 17-18)
    - Note regarding letters to family, undated (Folder 17: 1)
    - Letters to family, 1917-1923, undated (Folder 17: 2-11)
      Includes some letters from Truman Smith and Louis Moreau, as well as photographs.
    - "Life in Berlin,", 1919-1924 (Folder 17: 12)
      Includes correspondence of Truman Smith and Katharine A. H. Smith.
    - "Life in Berlin" (cont'd.), 1919-1924 (Folder 18: 1)
      Includes family photographs and reproductions of photographs used in "My Life" memoir.
    - Moreau, Louis, correspondence from battlefield, 1917 (Folder 18: 2)
    - "German Soldier Waiting to Go to Battle," typescript, 1918, undated (Folder 18: 3)
  - Letters to family, by subject, 1911-1969 (Box 18)
    - "Last months of war,", 1918 (Folder 18: 4)
    - Silver Star for bravery in the Argonne, 1917-1919 (Folder 18: 5)
      Includes book of the United States Army 3rd Infantry Division titled Third Division Citations (1919).
    - Battle of Bois de Forêt, Château-Theirry, Argonne, 1918-1919 (Folder 18: 6)
    - Landing in France, 1918 (Folder 18: 7)
    - "Life on the Mexican border,", 1911-1917 (Folder 18: 8)
    - Letters to family, 1915-1969 (Folder 18: 9)
  - Letters to Katharine A. H. Smith from France and Germany, 1918-1919, undated (Boxes 18-19)
    - Undated (Folder 18: 10)
    - 1918 (Folder 18: 11-12)
    - 1918 (cont'd.) (Folder 19: 1)
    - 1919 (Folder 19: 2-5)
  - Biographical file, 1913-1917 (Box 19)
    - Yale University clippings, photographs, and ephemera, 1913-1915 (Folder 19: 6)
      Includes some postcards depicting training exercises in Plattsville, New York and casualties on the Marne.
    - Marriage of Truman Smith to Katharine Alling Hollister, 1917 (Folder 19: 7)
  - Military personnel files of Truman Smith, 1919-1946 (Folder 20: 1-2)
    Copies of correspondence and efficiency reports, obtained from the National Personnel Records Center in St. Louis.
  - Infantry School, Fort Benning and Fort Leavenworth, files, 1926-1930 (Folder 20: 3-8)
    Includes correspondence to family, photographs, and teaching materials.
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, 1941-1945, 1973, 1986 (Box 20-21)
    - Smith, Kätchen (Katharine T.), correspondence, 1941-1945 (Folder 20: 9)
    - Smith, Kätchen (Katharine T.), correspondence (cont'd.), 1941-1945 (Folder 21: 1)
    - Beck, Alfred, correspondence regarding what G-2 thought about chances of war and relationship of Truman Smith and General von Boetticher, 1973 (Folder 21: 2-4)
    - Mosely, Leonard correspondence, 1986 (Folder 21: 5)
  - Correspondence of Kätchen Smith with various researchers interested in Truman Smith and collected materials regarding military attaché in Germany, 1965, 1990s-2000s (Folder 21: 6-16)
  - Subject file, 1944-1993 (Box 21)
    - G-2 (Military Intelligence Service), 1944-1984 (Box-folder 21: 17-18)
      - Collected clippings and correspondence, photocopies, 1944-1984 (Folder 21: 17)
      - War ration leather pouch, undated (Folder 21: 17)
      - Delaney, Edmund, letters and fragment of memoir (photocopy), 1944-1945, 1984 (Folder 21: 18)
    - Lindbergh, Charles, visits to Germany, 1945-1984 (Folder 21: 19-20)
    - Thompson, Paul, writings and photgraphs, 1980-1993 (Folder 21: 21)
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, 1919, 1935, 1945-1976 (Box 22)
    - "From the files of KAHS, 1935-1939, Germany" (Folder 22: 1)
      Includes an assortment of Christmas cards and ephemera from military attachés, members of the Luftwaffe and other German officials, 1935-1939. Also includes letters from General Werner von Blomberg, Erhard Milch, and others regarding Truman Smith's departure from Germany and a photograph of General Rüdel and his family.
    - Diaries, vols. I-III, 1919 (Folder 22: 2-4)
    - Guest lists of German civilians and army, Berlin, circa 1935 (Folder 22: 5)
    - Correspondence, clippings, and notes relating to German tactics and Pearl Harbor, 1945-1976 (Folder 22: 6-7)
  - United States Army documents relating to departure from Berlin, 1941 (Folder 22: 8)
  - Correspondence, 1924, 1945-1955, 1961-1970 (Box 22)
    - Clark, Carter, General, photocopy, 1969 (Folder 22: 9)
    - Mayer, Ferdinand, 1961-1970 (Folder 22: 10)
    - Smith, Katharine, regarding possible duel with Gerd von Buggenhagen, 1924 (Folder 22: 11)
    - Smith, Kätchen, regarding trip to Germany, typed copies, 1963 (Folder 22: 12)
      Includes copy of report titled "Estimate of the Combat Value of the German Army," 1963 December 15.
    - Speidel, Hans, regarding German war events and events leading up to NATO, photocopies, 1945-1955 (Folder 22: 13)
  - Diplomatic passport of Truman Smith, 1922 (Folder 22: 14)
  - Knox, H. J., Soldier Cartoons of the American Forces in Germany, Coblenz: Krabbensche Buchdruckerei, 1919 (Folder 22: 15)
  - Trip to Germany with new military attaché Major Allan Leonard to re-establish pre-war contacts with German military officers, photographs and correspondence, 1955 (Folder 22: 16-17)
  - Scrapbook (guestbook) of cards and telegrams, 1930s (Folder 23: 1)
    Includes entries by Adolf von Schell, Hermann Göring, Thea Rasche, and Erhard Milch.
  - "Truman Smith: 1893-1942, The Facts of Life: A Narrative with Documents," photocopy, 155 p. (Folder 23: 2)
  - Correspondence of Katharine A. H. Smith regarding trip to West Germany, 1968 (Folder 23: 3)
  - Letters regarding trips to Central America and Spain, 1960s (Folder 23: 4)
  - Published reviews of Berlin Alert, 1982-1984 (Folder 23: 5)
  - Speech by Truman Smith on Cold War analysis and defense of Europe, 1950 (Folder 23: 6)
  - Airpower Historian magazine, 1963 April (Folder 23: 7)
  - Freedom of Information file of Truman Smith, 1938-1978 (Folder 23: 8-10)
    Includes correspondence from Army Intelligence.
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, 1933-1992 (Boxes 23-24)
    - Lindbergh, Charles and Anne, correspondence (originals and photocopies) in response to death of Truman Smith, 1970-1974 (Folder 23: 11)
      Includes one photograph of the Lindberghs on a boat.
    - Condolence letters regarding death of Katharine A. H. Smith, 1992 (Folder 23: 12)
    - Miller, Dwight (Herbert Hoover Presidential Library), correspondence, 1978-1984 (Folder 23: 13)
    - Truman Smith biography, presumably written by Katharine A. H. Smith, 1970s (Folder 23: 14)
    - Katharine A. H. Smith biographical materials, 1981-1984 (Folder 23: 15)
    - Summary of conversation between Charles Lindbergh and Igor Sikorsky regarding atomic bomb, photocopy, 1976 (Folder 23: 16)
    - Correspondence with various researchers concerning Truman Smith and events in Berlin, 1974-1991 (Folder 23: 17)
    - Letters received, 1933-1990 (Folder 24: 1)
      Includes letters from Jacob Beam, Robert F. Bradford, Diane von Buggenhagen, President Gerald Ford, Ernst Hanfstaengl, Bob Hope, Stewart McKinney, Carlos Menottie, Mrs. Hans Speidel, and Dewitt Wallace. Includes photographs of Katharine A. H. Smith (1933) and Truman Smith (1920s).
    - Passport and drivers license, 1935-1939 (Folder 24: 2)
  - Letters received, 1937-1962 (Folder 24: 3)
    Includes letters from Rudolf Brickmann, William E. Dodd, Stanley D. Embick, [?] von Goblenz, Ernst Hanfstaengl, Herbert Hoover, Charles Lindbergh, George C. Marshall, John F. O'Ryan, General von Reichenau, Ernst Udet, Albert C. Wedemeyer, and Robert E. Wood.
  - Correspondence of Katharine T. Coley (Kätchen Smith) with Alexander Böker, German ambassador to the Vatican, 1979-1994 (Folder 24: 4)
  - Biographical file, 1970, 1975-1988 (Box 24)
    - Oral history interview with Truman Smith conducted by Ray Henze, bound volume, 1970 (Folder 24: 5)
    - Death of Truman Smith, 1975-1988 (Folder 24: 6)
      Includes clippings, citation, and certificates.
  - Writings and correspondence on death and legacy of Truman Smith, 1970-1971 (Folder 24: 7-8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1969, undated (Folder 24: 9)
    Includes itinerary and Christmas card.
  - Photographs, negatives, and postcards, 1933-1936, undated (Box 24)
    - Schofield Barracks, 1933-1935 (Folder 24: 10)
    - Truman Smith and other military attachés at maneuvers; Nuremburg rally; Truman Smith in Berlin; Lindbergh's arrival in Germany; Royal Reception Diplomatic Corps, the Hague; portraits of Truman Smith and Katharine A. H. Smith, 1935-1936, undated (Folder 24: 11)
    - Photographic negatives, for use in "My Life" memoir, undated (Folder 24: 12)
  - Katharine Alling Hollister Smith, 1977-1984, undated (Box 25)
    - Burdick, Charles and Milorad Drachkovitch, correspondence, 1977-1984 (Folder 25: 1-2)
    - List of reports sent from Berlin between 1935 and 1936, photocopy, undated (Folder 25: 3)
  - Biographical file, 1893-1971 (Boxes 25-26)
    - Death of Truman Smith, 1893-1971 (Box-folder 25: 4-11)
      Includes baptismal record, clippings, funeral booklet, photographs of grave at Arlington National Cemetery, and condolence telegrams.
    - Death of Truman Smith, condolences, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 26: 1-6)
  - Books by Hans Speidel, Ernst Hanfstaengl, and others, relating to Hitler, Normandy invasion, and German army, 1953-2002 (Box 27)
  - Oversize materials, 1916-1953 (Box 28)
    - Photographs, 1919-1953 (Folder 28: 1-2)
      Includes portraits of Tom Barber, Hamilton Bryan, Forrest Harding, Townsend B. Heard, Alan Houghton, Ralph Huebner, Clare Booth Luce, Ruth Bryan Owens, George C. Marshall, Paul Palmer, Rabe von Pappenheim, Dorst Patch, Paul Peabody, Walter Reichenau, Phillip Roosevelt, Adolf von Schell, Hans Speidel, Albert Wedemeyer, and Robert Woods.
    - Certificates, citations, and other identification documents, 1916-1939 (Folder 28: 3-4)
  - 4 reels of microfilm copies of papers of Truman Smith, 1916-1975, at the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library (Folder Microfilm cabinet)
    A description of the Truman Smith papers at the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library may be found at: https://hoover.archives.gov/research/collections/manuscriptfindingaids/smith.html
- 2013 Increment, 1919-1984 (Boxes 29-30)
  - Album of Berlin compiled by Katharine A. H. Smith, 1935 August - 1937 February (Box 29)
    Includes various photographs of Truman Smith and others, invitations, cards, postcards, and other ephemera.
  - Album of Berlin compiled by Katharine A. H. Smith, 1935, 1937-1938 (Box 30)
    Includes invitations, announcements, postcards, photographs, newspaper articles, tickets, invitations, and other ephemera. See memoirs of Katharine A. H. Smith for further information about the individuals and events. There are some notes by Katharine T. Coley (Kätchen) identifying individuals.
  - Guestbook, 1935-1939
    Signed by guest house visitors, including Charles and Anne Lindbergh, General Weidemer, Major Spiedel, Martha Dodd, and Amanda Dodd.
  - Album, Army of Occupation, Berlin, circa 1919-1922
    Photographs of individuals, scenery, landmark, and events in Germany.
  - Correspondence, Hoover Presidential Library Association, 1975-1984
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1939-1945, 1955 (Box 26)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2015 May release of records, 1939-1945 (Box-folder 26: 7)
    Telegram (1939); a report titled "War Potential and Intentions of European Axis Nations" (circa 1941); memoranda regarding organization of the Military Intelligence Division (MID) (1944); and a study on developments within the German Reich (1945).
  - 2016 January release of records, 1955 (Box-folder 26: 8)
    Letter from Robert A. Schow, Department of the Army, Office of the Assistant Chief of Staff, G-2, Intelligence, to Truman Smith regarding assignment in Germany, 18 May 1955.